Guide to the University of Pittsburgh Division of the Natural Sciences Office Files, 1956-1972 UA.90.4.2
ULS Archives & Special Collections
- Engineering and Mines, 1965-1967 (Box 24, Folder 184)
  Salary distribution, DNS and Engineering; correspondence on Junior Engineers' and Scientists' Summer Institute (JESSI); average salaries in natural sciences; papers by Dean Hollscher, "Principles, Problems, Models and Engineering," "The Omitted Link," "An Arrow or a Wheel," "Bharat in New Clothes," and "The Industrialization of Developing Countries"; "A Sylogism on Mathematics" prepared by Engineering Undergraduate Administrative Committee; paper on "A New Undergraduate Program" School of Engineering; math placement test.
- Enrollment Data, 1961-1966 (Box 24, Folder 185)
  Comparative enrollment data, spring trimesters, 1960-1962; comparative enrollment report, 1961/1962 and 1962/1963; enrollment analyses 1965/1966; correspondence on room capacity; enrollment data 200 and 300 series; enrollment model for X year.
- Faculty Club, 1960-1967 (Box 24, Folder 186)
- Faculty Club, 1964-1965 (Box 24, Folder 187)
  Proficiency in research, graduate teaching and undergraduate teaching.
- Fellowships, 1958-1967 (Box 24, Folder 188)
  Announcements and correspondence concerning ads, including the A.W. Mellon Fellowship.
- Foundations, 1958-1967 (Box 24, Folder 189)
  Announcements about study grants; Scaife Foundation and the 1958 death of Alan Scaife; grant from Benedum Foundation, 1962; Foundation for the Study of Cycles; proposed grant from Kresge Foundation; list of Pittsburgh based foundations.
- Foundations - Dedication of Buhl Laboratories in Clapp Hall, 1959-1960 (Box 24, Folder 190)
- Foundations - Correspondence, 1959-1967 (Box 24, Folder 191)
- Foundations - National Science Cooperative Graduate Fellowship, 1959-1960 (Box 24, Folder 192)
  Award letters and records of payment, 1959-1960; summer fellowships, 1959-1960; summer fellowships for graduate teaching assistants and award letters to fellows, 1959; summer fellowships for grad teaching assistants, award letters, and correspondence, 1960.
- Foundations - National Science Cooperative Graduate Fellowship, 1960-1961 (Box 25, Folder 193)
  Award letters and correspondence, 1960-1961; summer fellowships for graduate teaching assistants, award letters, and correspondence, 1961.
- Foundations - National Science Cooperative Graduate Fellowship, 1961-1962 (Box 25, Folder 194)
  Award letters and correspondence; Regional Congress on NSF Fellowship Programs; summer fellowships for graduate teaching assistants, award letters, and correspondence, 1962.
- Foundations - National Science Cooperative Graduate Fellowship, 1962-1963 (Box 25, Folder 195)
  Award letters and correspondence, 1962-1963; graduate and summer fellowship correspondence, 1962-1963; summer fellowships for graduate teaching assistants, 1963.
- Foundations - National Science Cooperative Graduate Fellowship, 1964-1965 (Box 25, Folder 196)
  Co-op graduate and summer fellowships, 1953-1964; memos and correspondence by Dr. Lauffer, summer fellowships, 1964; co-op graduate fellowships, 1964-1965; summer fellowships, 1965.
- Foundations - National Science Cooperative Graduate Fellowship, 1965-1966 (Box 25, Folder 197)
  Summer fellowships, 1966; co-op graduate fellowship, 1966-1967; graduate fellows, 1965-1966; graduate fellows, 1966-1967.
- Foundations - National Science Graduate Trainees, 1964-1967 (Box 25, Folder 198)
  Graduate trainees, 1964-1967, and summer trainees, 1966-1967.
- Foundations - National Science Institutional Grant Correspondence, 1961-1963 (Box 25, Folder 199)
- Foundations - National Science Senior Foreign Scientist Fellowships, 1962-1965 (Box 25, Folder 200)
  Announcements, forms, correspondence, awardees, and nominees.
- Foundations - National Science Senior Foreign Scientist Fellowships, 1965-1967 (Box 25, Folder 201)
- Foundations - Sloan, 1964-1966 (Box 26, Folder 202)
  Memo from Dean Halliday to Dr. Litchfield on engineering grant; copy of proposal "A Dual-Stem Program for the Education and Training of Engineers."
- General Correspondence, 1958-1962 (Box 26, Folder 203)
  List of buildings and room assignments; correspondence about Freshman Comp, 1958; midday series programs; inquiry about positions; inquiries about university programs; memo on Khrushchev's visit; United Fund; John Scott award; letter from Dr. Lauffer to Agnes L. Starrett about her book "History of the University of Pittsburgh"; St. Edmund's Academy uses lecture room in Clapp Hall.
- General Correspondence, 1962-1967 (Box 26, Folder 204)
  United Fund Campaign; St. Edmund's Christmas Lecture for high school science students; Mayor's Prayer Breakfast for J.M. Barr; invitation to Steven Dedijer of Denmark to deliver lecture; National Medal of Science; Hill Education Project; credit of tuition allowance for student Jesse Corlis, son of eminent scientist Dr. Lester Corlis; correspondence on RIAS (Research Institute for Advanced Study) Baltimore; tables showing academic progress of football players; use of Clapp Hall by St. Edmund's Academy.
- General Studies, 1958-1962 (Box 26, Folder 205)
  Memos on programs and procedures; time schedules of classes; brochures; announcements.
- General Studies, 1962-1967 (Box 26, Folder 206)
- Government Agencies, 1946-1960 (Box 26, Folder 207)
  Letters congratulating University of Pittsburgh on aid in war effort; U.S. Information Agency requests catalogs; information from Armed Services Technical Information Agency to assist a Department of Defense Contract; correspondence from U.S. Army Chemical Center; correspondence from U.S. Public Health Service; correspondence about office of Naval Research.
- Government Agencies, 1960-1961 (Box 26, Folder 208)
  Correspondence with office of Naval Research; Army Chemical Center; correspondence on federal grants; NASA recruiting drive; quotations to U.S. Air Force; University of Pittsburgh Air correspondence; National Academy of Sciences, National Research Council; Air Force Chemistry grant and contract research.
- Government Agencies, 1958-1961 (Box 26, Folder 209)
  Air Research and Development Command, 1958/1959-1960/1961; correspondence on University of Pittsburgh fields of interest; "Basic Research in the Air Force"; memos.
- Government Agencies - Atomic Energy Commission, 1960-1966 (Box 26, Folder 210)
- Government Agencies, 1962-1963 (Box 27, Folder 211)
  NASA; Regional Industrial Development Corp. (RIDC); conference announcements; related activities at the University of Pittsburgh paper; proposal for RIDC facility in Pittsburgh; "Research in the Division of the Natural Science" by M.A. Lauffer; memo on proposal to Department of Defense and copies of info sent to Secretary of Defense Robert S. McNamara; space related activities at the University of Pittsburgh.
- Government Agencies - Public Health Service, 1960-1963 (Box 27, Folder 212)
  Regulations for research programs; correspondence with congressman urging creation of Institute of General Medical Sciences in National Institute of Health; Dr. Lauffer invited to join General Medical Sciences Council.
- Governor's Council of Science and Technology, 1962-1963 (Box 27, Folder 213)
  Clipping about setting up council, April 5, 1963; Dr. Halliday accepts membership in the Council, Chancellor also a member; agendas and minutes; membership list; "Changing Manpower Needs in Pennsylvania" report; Council assignments; Dr. Halliday's recommendations for major national scientific committees; proposed duties of committee on research trends; Report of Education Committee assessing higher education in Pennsylvania.
- Governor's Council of Science and Technology, 1963-1965 (Box 27, Folder 214)
  Roster of Federal Government Commission and Advisory Committees in the Sciences; list of Pitt faculty recommended for Government Committees; roster of Army scientific advisory panel; list of top 25 Department of Defense Contractors; paper, "Minerals in future of Pennsylvania related to science needs"; roster of Pitt personnel who could aid state in industrial planning; list of new technologies recommendations of Research Trends Communications to Governor on furthering research in Pennsylvania; correspondence on state aid to higher education.
- Governor's Council of Science and Technology Meetings, 1963-1964 (Box 27, Folder 215)
  Notices, agendas, and minutes; Geographical distribution of NASA appropriations, 1963; report of Committee on Scientific personnel; agenda and discussion of meeting in Washington D.C., October 16, 1963; progress reports on Committee on Research trends, April 1964.
- Governor's Council of Science and Technology - Committee on Research, 1964 (Box 28, Folder 216)
  Trends Survey, Replies from letter sent to 383 Pennsylvania leaders in science, engineering, business, education and government asking them to evaluate trends in science and technology, 1964; National Academy of Science publication: Proposed US program for "International Years of the Quiet Sun 1964-65."
- Governor's Council of Science and Technology, 1963-1964 (Box 28, Folder 217)
  Reports from Pennsylvania leaders in education and industry on future of Pennsylvania's resources and technological development with index.
- Governor's Council of Science and Technology, 1963-1964 (Box 28, Folder 218)
  Reports on Pennsylvania's future and summaries for final report of Committee.
- Governor's Council of Science and Technology, 1963-1964 (Box 29, Folder 219)
  Two drafts of final report of Committee on Research Trends of Future Important Economic Potential prepared for Governor's Council on Science and Technology, June and July 1964.
- Governor's Council of Science and Technology, 1963-1964 (Box 29, Folder 220)
  Draft of final report of Governor's Council including list of scientists in Pennsylvania suggested to Federal agencies as competent for service, June 29, 1964; recommendations for educational policies; Proposals for atomic energy; research and technology as source of economic growth.
- Governor's Council of Science and Technology, 1963-1964 (Box 29, Folder 221)
  Final published report of the Council, summary and supplement which includes Report of Education Committee, Report of Scientific Industry Promotion Committee and Report of Committee on Research Trends, September 1964.
- Gow, S. Steele - Coordinated Education Center, 1962-1963 (Box 29, Folder 222)
  Correspondence on improved instruction in Mathematics and Science; memo from Steele Gow to head of Center about pre-college math and science instruction; report on Frick School; brochure describing Center; memo on pre-college math/science program; description of Schenley High School programs and value to University; plan for Educational Research. The Center became the Learning and Research Development Center in 1963/1964.
- Graduate School Public and International Affairs, 1958-1967 (Box 29, Folder 223)
  List of faculty in natural sciences; memo from Dean Stone to Dean Halliday about minor adjustment in faculty employment bylaws; correspondence and draft of Ph.D. oral examination of Philip Kronenberg, GSPIA Ph.D. candidate on Public Policy Statement-US Manned Space Program.
- Committee on Graduate Study, 1957-1960 (Box 29, Folder 224)
- Committee on Graduate Study, 1960-1961 (Box 30, Folder 225)
- Committee on Graduate Study, 1961-1963 (Box 30, Folder 226)
  Notices, minutes, discussion papers; report of Committee on Ph.D. programs; policy for MS program; regional campuses.
- Committee on Graduate Study, 1963-1967 (Box 30, Folder 226A)
- Graduate Faculty Meetings, 1957-1959 (Box 30, Folder 227)
- Graduate Faculty Meetings, 1959-1961 (Box 30, Folder 228)
- Graduate Faculty Meetings, 1961-1962 (Box 30, Folder 229)
- Graduate Study, 1958-1959 (Box 30A, Folder 230)
  Agendas and memos of Councils on Graduate Study, Graduate Faculty and University Council on Graduate Study; appointments to graduate faculty; report of Committee on Admission policies; plan to develop graduate fellowships; statement of purpose and regulations for Westinghouse Electric fellowship and doctoral programs; reports on recruiting graduate assistantships.
- Graduate Study, 1959-1960 (Box 30A, Folder 231)
  Agenda and minutes, Councils on Graduate Study; memos on Admissions; memo on National Science Foundation fellowships; paper on graduate program on musicology; examination for graduate students issued by University Testing Service; Wainwright House notice on scholarships; notices to faculty to serve on Graduate Study Committee.
- Graduate Study, 1959-1960 (Box 31, Folder 232)
  Graduate faculty appointments and biographical information; memos on graduate student assistantships; data on math assistantships at other universities; papers on foreign language requirement; reports on recruitment; registration instructions; reports on stipends; paper on style and form for theses and dissertations; appointments.
- Graduate Study, 1960-1961 (Box 31, Folder 233)
  Agendas, meetings, papers on Councils of Graduate Study; report of Committee for reappraisal of graduate study; distribution of graduate students by major, department, and load carried, Fall 1960/1961; graduate faculty appointments including biographical information; list of graduate faculty; memo on foreign language exam; Ph.D. regulations; minutes of graduate student organization; reports or University examination for graduate students.
- Graduate Study, 1961-1962 (Box 31, Folder 234)
  Memos on election of Council on Graduate Study; minutes; degrees granted by major area, 1960/1961; graduate faculty appointments and biographical information; report of Committee on appointment of "Dean of Graduate Teaching Assistants"; language requirements; census of post doctoral people at Pitt; graduate students employed in industry.
- Graduate Study, 1962-1963 (Box 32, Folder 235)
  Minutes of Graduate Council Disciplines, Council on Graduate Study Health Professions, and University Council on Graduate Study; admissions data; papers on recruiting African American college students; census on post doctoral people; graduate faculty listing and appointments including biographical information; memos on language requirements; memos on post doctoral study; recruitment.
- Graduate Study, 1963-1964 (Box 32, Folder 236)
  Memos on various aspects of graduate study; minutes of Councils of Graduate Study: Disciplines, Health Profession, and University Council; data on graduate admissions; memo on stipends; census of post doctoral study; memos on graduate assistants; language requirement.
- Graduate Study, 1963-1964 (Box 32, Folder 237)
  List of graduate faculty appointments including biographies.
- Graduate Study, 1964-1965 (Box 32, Folder 238)
  Policy on graduate assistants; proposed policy for admission; census of post doctoral study; list of faculty terminations; graduate faculty appointments including biographies; minutes of Councils: Disciplines, Health Professions, and University Council; language requirement.
- Graduate Study, 1965-1966 (Box 32, Folder 239)
  Definition of full time student; faculty terminations; faculty appointments includes biographies; list of graduate faculty; census of post doctoral study; recruitment.
- Graduate Study, 1966-1967 (Box 33, Folder 240)
  List of Ph.D.s earned at Pennsylvania institutions, 1961/1962; policy on graduate student teaching; language requirement; procedures for foreign student admissions; census of post doctoral study; graduate faculty appointments including biographies.
- Graduate Study, 1966-1967 (Box 33, Folder 241)
  Minutes of the Councils of Graduate Study: Disciplines and University Council.
- Graduate Study - Promotional Materials, 1960-1966 (Box 33, Folder 242)
- Granting Agencies, 1958-1966 (Box 33, Folder 243)
  News release of Monsanbo Chemical Scholarship for employees; Research Corps invitation to awards; American Gas Association research proposal for developing gas air conditioner, Sperry and Hutchinson grant brochure; National Academy of Science post doctoral grants; Research Corporation bulletin.
- Grunbaum, Adolf - Philosophy of Science, 1960-1965 (Box 33, Folder 244)
  Schedules of lectures; correspondence on lectures series; letter to Vice Chancellor Peake from Dr. Englesberg, Bacteriology, on importance of Philosophy of Science program; typescript of an article by A. Grunbaum, "Temporally-Asymmetric Principles, Parity between Explanation and Prediction, and Mechanism vs. Teleology"; memo on philosophy in academic program; correspondence on natural sciences students taking philosophy courses; syllabus for Philosophy 181: Philosophy of the Natural Sciences and Philosophy 257: Philosophy of Space and Time; short descriptions of other courses; Pittsburgh Press article on Pitt philosophers and scientists, 1963; letter about grant for Philosophy course.
- Health Professions, 1958-1963 (Box 33, Folder 245)
  Correspondence about science requirements for Medical School; correspondence on education in Pharmacy; description of Biochemistry 261 and 262; seminar announcements, Department of Biochemistry and Nutrition, 1961/1962; ad hoc committee microbiology search, seminar announcements; announcements, Public Health seminars, 1962/1963; School of Medicine statement on discrimination, 1963.
- Health Professions, 1963-1964 (Box 33, Folder 246)
  List of contributors to symposium; research issuer in public health and population change; candidates for Biochemistry Department Chairman including vitae; School of Medicine seminar announcements; proposal for Biochemistry graduate program, 1964; correspondence and vitae, Biochemistry search committee; WPIC council meeting agendas and minutes; Dr. Hans Noll award from American Cancer Society; seminar notices for microbiology.
- Health Professions, 1964-1967 (Box 33, Folder 247)
  List of faculty areas of activity in Graduate School of Public Health; proposed search training program in dental education; future development of University position paper, 1965; vitae of candidates for Biochemistry; seminar announcements; budget for Western Psychiatric and Staunton Clinic, 1965/1966; development of Child Study Center at Arsenal Family Child Center; memo on program to train mental health workers; tribute to Dr. James Crabtree, Graduate School Public Health; news release on $3.2 million from Mellon Trust for Neurology; seminar notices, School of Medicine; correspondence and minutes of Western Psychiatric Institute Council.
- Higher Education Act, 1965-1967 (Box 34, Folder 248)
  List of offices for administering act; appropriations list; notes on government offices of interest for funding; description of Titles I and III of Act.
- Hill Education Projects, 1966-1967 (Box 34, Folder 249)
  Paper on Tutorials on disadvantaged children; Tutor's guidelines; constitution for Hill project, 1963 and 1966revision; Dean Halliday appointed advisor to project, 1966; information on Big Brothers program; correspondence on composition of advisory board for project; Hill Project made a student organization; memo about Dean Halliday resignation as advisor, September 19, 1967; operating budget, 1967-1968.
- Housing, 1962-1965 (Box 34, Folder 250)
- Internal Revenue Service, Fellowship and Stipend Income Tax, 1957-1965 (Box 34, Folder 251)
- International Dimensions Program, 1962-1964 (Box 34, Folder 252)
- International Dimensions Program, 1964-1966 (Box 34, Folder 253)
- International Studies Program, 1966-1967 (Box 34, Folder 254)
  International Education bill proposal; background paper; committee on awards; announcement of International Study residence program in Latin America, January 19, 1967; report to the members of the policy Planning and Coordinating Committee, February 1967; draft of brochure "Summarization of International Activities at University of Pittsburgh;" paper listing extracts from Grant Data Quarterly.
- Laboratory Fees, 1958-1967 (Box 34, Folder 255)
- Latin American Activities, 1962-1964 (Box 34, Folder 256)
  Faculty and staff activities in Latin America; correspondence about Ecuador Program's biologist needs; reports submitted by T.H. Dunkelberger, Professor of Chemistry from Ecuador; correspondence on Geology Program in Ecuador and proposal; correspondence about Galapagos Islands Expedition of the University of California; Dr. Litchfield appoints Ambassador Willard L. Beaulac as consultant on Latin American program; Lowell C. Day appointed as campus coordinator of Ecuador project; brochure "Focus, Latin America;" correspondence on plans for a Guatemala program.
- Latin American Activities, 1964-1965 (Box 35, Folder 257)
  Ecuador project: correspondence on Ecuador Biology program; T.H. Dunkelberger chemistry reports from Ecuador; Quarterly reports of Ecuador Project, August 1963-March 1965; positions to be staffed.
- Latin American Activities, 1965-1968 (Box 35, Folder 258)
  Certificate program in Latin America studies; Ecuador Project correspondence; development of biology textbook "La Ciencia de las Plantas" by S.N. Postlethwait; T.H. Dunkelberger chemistry reports from Ecuador; memo on Physics in Ecuador Project; policy paper on staffing for Ecuador Project; Quarterly reports of Ecuador Project, June-December 1965; Biology in Central University, final report by R. Buchsbaum, July 30, 1966; End of tour report by E.V. Miller the biology-short-term consultant Ecuador Project; paper on Development of higher education in Ecuador with reference to the Pittsburgh cooperation, November 29, 1966; Achievement report, May 1963-April 1967.
- Learning Research and Development Center, 1963-1964 (Box 35, Folder 259)
  Paper describing LRDC, October 1963; "Responsive Education Continuum (RECon) Proposal," July 15, 1964; "Research and Development Centers Proposal" submitted to the U.S Commissioner of Education, December 10, 1963.
- Learning Research and Development Center, 1964-1967 (Box 35, Folder 260)
  Invitation to Dean Halliday to serve on Learning Council; paper describing purpose and objectives of LRDC; newspaper clippings; announcement of lecture series.
- Liberal Arts, 1958-1960 (Box 35, Folder 261)
  Memos about grade distribution, registration, course structures, and outline of proposed degree requirements; BA and BS candidates for graduation, April 1960.
- Liberal Arts, 1960-1964 (Box 35, Folder 262)
  Hamilton Watch award; memos on degree requirements, courses, and registration; honors program policy paper; copy of material for 1964/1965 bulletin; Committee on Undergraduate Preparation for the Study of Medicine; search for deanship.
- Liberal Arts, 1964-1967 (Box 35, Folder 263)
  Curriculum Committee; removal of G grades; search for deanship; Academic Assembly meetings; admission with advanced standing; dean's list, 1965/1966; academic organization chart; list of students graduating in liberal arts with major in a science giving QPA; General Interest Notes, 1966-1967; Freshman Support Program Final Report, 1965-1966; underclass advising; report of the Honors Committee, July 29, 1966; list of candidates for BS degree in School of Liberal Arts (SLA); report on the SLA for 1965/1966 and 1966/1967; paper "Reflections on the Graduate Student in Undergraduate Instruction;" division by division summary of SLA instructional needs.
- Library, 1957-1962 (Box 35, Folder 264)